Guide to the William Lukes Collection of Houston Photographic Research Materials, 1969-1974 MS 531
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
William Lukes Collection of Houston Photographic Research Materials
1969-1974
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Lukes, William C., 1949-
MS 531
2.5 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
The collection consists of photographic research materials on Houston, TX, Rice University, and various urban scenes, architectural details, and photographic techniques. It was created by William Lukes in collaboration with Paul Hester during the years 1969 through 1974, when Lukes was an architectural student at Rice University.
Biographical / Historical
William Lukes is a residential and commercial architect and free-lance photographer in Carbondale, CO. He received his BA in Architecture and Fine Arts (Photography) in 1971 and a Master of Architecture in 1974 from the Rice University School of Architecture. Lukes has worked with artists Richard Hunt and Isamu Noguchi, and his photographs have been published in books and magazines. Lukes is a member of the American Institute of Architects and is licensed by the states of Colorado and California.
Paul Hester is an architectural photographer and lecturer in the Department of Visual and Dramatic Arts at Rice University in Houston, TX. He received his BA in Art from Rice University in 1971 and an MFA from the Rhode Island School of Design in 1976. Hester has received grants from the National Endowment for the Arts, and exhibited his work at the Menil Collection, Rice University, the University of Houston College of Architecture, and the Houston Public Library. He has also published extensively in books and magazines.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of photographic research materials on Houston compiled by William Lukes, architect and Rice University graduate, from 1969 through 1974. The photos were taken by Lukes in collaboration with Paul Hester, and were used in a number of publications and papers concerning the development of Houston, inventorying and cataloguing the growth of Houston neighborhoods, and recording various architectural landmarks in the Houston area during the period. Also included are student work from the Rice Media Center, and a photographic essay of anti-war protests (Viet Nam war) in Houston and at Rice.
Series I of the collection includes photographs and negatives related to Houston architecture, development, and events. Series II includes photographs and negatives of Rice University and Rice students, and portfolios, papers, and photographs for architecture and photography classes taken by Lukes from 1969 through 1974. Series III includes photographs and negatives of various urban scenes, architectural details, and experiments in photographic techniques by Lukes.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Accruals
No future additions are expected for this material.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated by its primary creator, William Lukes, a Rice University graduate and architect.
Arrangement
Correspondence in this collection is contained within two legal-sized document boxes and one oversize box measuring 2.5 linear feet. The collection is arranged topically by series in order of importance to the collection, with the American Institute of Architects Houston guidebook first. The collection is in good condition.
Index Terms
Subjects
Architecture; Rice University--History; Vietnam War (1961-1975); Twentieth century
Document Types
photographs
Places
Texas--Houston
Subjects (Persons)
Hester, Paul, 1948-; Lukes, William C., 1949-
- Series I: Houston, 1969-1974, n.d.; 238773
  Scope and Contents note
  This section contains photographs and negatives of Houston architecture and historical events.
  - Houston: An Architectural Guide. Edited by Peter C. Papademetriou. Houston,TX: Houston Chapter, American Institute of Architects, 1972; 238797 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - AIA guidebook negatives, areas 2, 8, 9 North, 1971- 1972; 238796 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - AIA guidebook negatives, area 1 Downtown, 1971- 1972; 238795 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - AIA guidebook negatives and contact sheets, 1971- 1972; 238794 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - AIA guidebook negatives, areas 3, 10, 11 East, 1971-1972; 238793 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - AIA guidebook negatives, areas 4, 12 South, 1971-1972; 238792 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - AIA guidebook negatives, areas 5, 13 Southwest, 1971-1972; 238791 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - AIA guidebook negatives, areas 6, 14 West, 1971-1972; 238790 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - AIA guidebook negatives, area 16 NASA to Galveston, 1971-1972; 238789 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Redding Road photographic portfolio, 1971; 238788 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Astrodome complex, n.d.; 238787 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Downtown Houston, 1970-1972; 238786 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Garden Apartments, n.d.; 238785 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Houston Mobile Home Show, 1971-1972; 238784 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Parade, Houston,TX., n.d.; 238783 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Parking Lots and Swimming Pools, 1971; 238782 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Pleasantville Apartments, East Houston. Brookover, William, William Lukes, and Mitchell Mize. Pleasantville. Houston: Rice University, 1970. (Report prepared as a joint feasibility study for the Federal Housing Authority and the First Unitarian Church of Houston), 238781 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Houston scenes by Paul Hester, n.d.; 238780 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Houston scenes, 1969-1974; 238779 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Houston scenes, 1971-1972; 238778 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Houston: small town parade, July 1970; 238777 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Oversize box: Houston: An Architectural Guide (AIA) oversize prints, 1972; 238776 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Oversize box: Redding Road Photographic Portfolio oversize prints, 1971; 238775 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Oversize box: Children, Pleasantville Apartments, East Houston oversize prints, 1970; 238774 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Series II: Rice University, 1969-1974, n.d.; 238761
  This section contains photographs and negatives of Rice University, and class materials from architecture and photography classes at Rice.
  - Rice anti- Viet Nam war convocation, April 1970; 238772 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Rice: Allen Center (anti- Viet Nam war convocation), April 1970; 238771 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Rice: Dean's Office (anti- Viet Nam war convocation), April 1970; 238770 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Class materials: Architecture 306b. Lukes, William. "Human Needs Satisfaction and Housing." Research paper, Rice University, 1971; 238769 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Lukes, William. "The Future of the Barrios." Research paper, Rice University, 1973; 238768 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Rice Media Center Class Project, 1970-1972; 238767 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Rice Media Center, n.d.; 238766 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Portfolio I, 1970; 238765 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Rice University scenes, n.d.; 238764 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Autry House, 1970; 238763 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Oversize box: Rice Anti- Viet Nam war convocation oversize print, April 1970; 238762 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Series III: Urban scenes,architectural details, photographic techniques, 1969-1974, n.d.; 238747
  This section contains photographs and negatives of various urban scenes, architectural details, and photographic techniques.
  - William Lukes, n.d.; 238760 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Paul Hester, 1970-1971; 238759 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Architectural details, urban landscapes, 238758 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Cowboy band, 238757 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Diner, 1974; 238756 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    General
    Photograph by Paul Hester.
  - Paired Images negatives, n.d.; 238755 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Paired Images prints, n.d.; 238754 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Houston nudes, 1969-1970; 238753 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Tattoo party, April 1970; 238752 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Various lens: Houston, beach, other, 1970; 238751 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Various lens-moving, n.d.; 238750 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Galveston, TX, n.d.; 238749 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Oversize box: Urban scenes, architectural details, photographic techniques oversize prints, n.d.; 238748 (Box 3, Folder 5)